Register of the Institute of Economic Affairs (Great Britain) records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Arthur Seldon File, 1941-1987
  - Speeches and writings
    - Lecture, Builders Merchants' Federation, 1980 March 28 (Folder 5)
      See Lecture, Yorkshire and Humberside annual dinner, Confederation of British Industry (CBI).
    - "The Use of Sample Polling to Construct a Hypothetical Demand for Welfare and to Measure the 'Fiction' of a Social Welfare Function,", 1980 April
      See Subject file/European Public Choice Society meetings/1980 Florence.
    - Lecture, St. Lawrence Jewry, Next Guildhall, London, 1980 April 30 (Folder 6)
      Notes and correspondence. See also General/Lecture notes.
    - "British Economic Policy," lecture, Köln (Germany), notes, 1980 May 15 (Folder 7)
    - "Moving Nearer the Market," Universities Quarterly 34/3, 1980 Summer (Folder 8)
      Typescript, off-print, and correspondence. Includes transcript of discussion between Alec Merrison, Maurice Peston, and Boris Ford.
    - Opening remarks, I.E.A. conference on local government, London, 1980
      Notes and tables. Proceedings subsequently published under the title Town Hall Power or Whitehall Pawn? Includes also draft papers. See CONFERENCE AND SEMINAR PROCEEDINGS/1980.
    - "Why We Need a Free Market in Health," Now!, 1980 June 27
      See The Litmus Papers... / Galleys of A. Seldon's contributions.
    - Review of Michael Novak (ed.), Denigration of Capitalism, British Journal of Industrial Relations, typescript and correspondence, 1979, 1980 June 30 (Folder 9)
    - "British Politics and the Case Against 'Socialized Medicine,'" lecture, Stanford University course at Cliveden, St. Thomas's Hospital Medical School, London, Notes, course program, and correspondence, 1980 July 4 (Folder 10)
    - "Socialism's Record Called into Question," letter to the editor, Times, printed copy and correspondence, 1980 August 6 (Folder 11)
    - "United Kingdom," Fraser Institute symposium on taxation, Vancouver, 1980 August 28-29
      - Background material (Folder 12)
      - Typescript. Includes "Comments on Arthur Seldon's Paper" by Alan Walters and "Response to Alan Walters" by A. Seldon (Folder 13)
      - Conference papers (Box 357, Folder 1-2)
      - Correspondence
        - Michael Walker. Includes correspondence with Alan Walters as well as his "Comments on Arthur Seldon's Paper," and Arthur Seldon's "Response to Alan Walters,"
          - 1980 - 1981 February (Folder 3)
          - 1981 March - 1982 (Folder 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous. Re holiday in Canada (Folder 6)
    - "Politics in the 'Unsordid' N.H.S.," Daily Telegraph, Typescript, galleys, and correspondence, 1980 September (Folder 7)
    - "Charging for Health Services," lecture, Adam Smith Institute, Windsor Castle, Notes, conference program, and correspondence, 1980 October 2 (Folder 8)
    - "Good Health, You'll Need It," Daily Telegraph, Typescript and printed copy, 1980 October 20 (Folder 9)
    - "Lower Taxes and More Welfare? Reason or Unreason in Public Opinion?" Forum on Taxing and Spending, Typescript, 1980 November (Folder 10)
    - "Industry and Government as Employer: A Disturbing Contrast," Times, Typescript, 1980 November 5 (Folder 11)
    - Comments on course members' presentations, Advanced Management Development Programme 6, Institute of Local Government Studies (INLOGOV), University of Birmingham (Great Britain), [?]. Correspondence and background material, 1980 November 6 (Folder 12)
    - "Patients Should Call Tune," letter to the editor, Daily Telegraph, Typescript and printed copy, 1980 November 8 (Folder 13)
    - Participation in round-table discussion re N.H.S., Friday Live, Tyne Tees Television, Correspondence, 1980 November 14 (Box 358, Folder 1)
    - "The N.H.S.: Is there a Better Way?" lecture, Conservative Medical Society Symposium, London, Notes and correspondence, 1980 November 15 (Folder 2)
    - "Local Government Imperialism: A View from the Outside," Society of Local Authority Chief Executives (SOLACE) Seminar, London, Subsequently published in The Gift to See Ourselves as Others See Us, SOLACE Occasional Paper, 1982 November 17. Notes, typescript, and correspondence. Includes galleys of the same article to be published in unidentified journal, 1983 (Folder 3-4)
    - "A New Debate on Financing Welfare," letter to the editor, Times, Typescript, 1980 November 20 (Folder 5)
    - Interview on Newsweek, British Broadcasting Corporation TV, Correspondence, 1980 November 28 (Folder 6)
    - Presentation and comments, conference on education, Clark University, Worcester, Massachusetts, Notes, correspondence, and conference program, 1980 December 5-6 (Folder 7)
    - "Why the Government Has Faltered and How It Can Recover," sent to Daily Telegraph and Financial Weekly, Typescript and correspondence, 1980 December 15 (Folder 8)
    - "British 'New Economic Policy': Mrs. Thatcher's Return to Liberalism," Journal of Contemporary Studies, See Correspondence/Institute for Contemporary Studies, circa 1981
    - Lecture, quarterly East Grinstead Constituency Council meeting, Sussex, Correspondence, 1981 January 15 (Folder 9)
    - "Litmus Test Shows Blue," Hospital Doctor, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence. Includes sample issue of Hospital Doctor, 1981-1980 (Folder 10)
    - Participation in round-table discussion re health on Current Account, British Broadcasting Corporation Scotland, Correspondence, 1981 January 20 (Folder 11)
    - "Most Public Services Are Not Public Goods," seminar on charging for public services, Civil Service College, Sunningdale Park, Ascot (Great Britain), Notes, correspondence, seminar program, and clippings. Includes paper by A. Peacock, 1981 February 9 (Folder 12)
    - "The Limits of State Intervention," lecture, School of Advanced Urban Studies, University of Bristol, Correspondence, syllabus, brochure, and background material, 1981 February 19 and 1982 March 4 (Folder 13)
    - Presentation and comments, Advanced Management Development Programme 7, Institute of Local Government Studies (INLOGOV), University of Birmingham, Notes, background material, syllabus, and correspondence, 1981 March 5 (Folder 14)
    - "The Inevitability of Capitalism," lecture, Economists Society, City University, London, Notes, typescript, and correspondence, 1981 March 10 (Box 359, Folder 1)
    - Lecture, Sussex Group Young Conservatives, University of Sussex, Brighton, Notes and correspondence, 1981 April 5 (Folder 2)
    - "The Inevitability of Capitalism," lecture, Socialist Party of Great Britain, Guildford Branch, Guildford (Great Britain), Notes and correspondence, 1981 May 8 (Folder 3)
    - "Now, a Seven Year Plan for Mrs. Thatcher," Accountancy, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1981 July (Folder 4)
    - "The Welfare State Is Withering Away," lecture, summer school conference, International University of the Open Society, Cambridge (Great Britain), Subsequently published in International Background, vol. 9, no. 10, and Reason. Typescripts (speech and article version) and correspondence. For printed copy and a different version see also Subject file/Mont Pèlerin Society Meetings/1981 Stockholm (Sweden) (Folder 5)
    - "Market Principles in Social Welfare," lecture, administration trainee course, Civil Service College, London, Notes and correspondence, 1981 July 10 (Folder 6)
    - Brief on health and education, social services seminar, Conservative Research Department, Westminster, London, Seminar program, summaries, and correspondence. Includes paper by C. Mockler, 1981 July 16 (Folder 7)
    - "SDP: Graffiti on the Wall That Means the End of Labour," Daily Telegraph, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1981 November 9 (Folder 8)
    - "Pro-Private," Seminar on Health Financing, Civil Service College, Sunningdale Park, Ascot (Great Britain), Notes, correspondence, seminar program, and clippings, 1981 November 23 (Folder 9)
    - "Crosby: Euphoria and Reality," letter to the editor, Times, Typescript, 1981 November 30 (Folder 10)
    - "Round the World in 3750 Words: In Search of Family Sovereignty in Education," A. Martino (ed.?), [English translation of Italian book title: Financing Education in a Free Society], Typescript and correspondence with A. Martino et al. Includes C.R.E.A. brochure and press release, 1982 (Folder 11)
    - "The Secret of 'Socialism:' Promised Land or Spoof?" Daily Telegraph, Typescript and correspondence, 1982 (Folder 12)
    - "Promises, Promises, but not National Insurance," Daily Telegraph, See also "The Secret of Socialism," 1982, 1982 January 7 (Folder 13)
    - "Welfare State - Bitter Fruit," Daily Telegraph, Typescript, 1982 February (Folder 14)
    - Letter to the editor, Times, Typescript, 1982 February 10 (Folder 15)
    - "Health Partnership" and "No Future for N.H.S.," letters to the editor, Times, Typescript and printed copy, 1982 February 17 and March 3 (Folder 16)
    - "Equality in Social Policy," lecture, staff-student seminar, Personal Social Services Research Unit, University of Kent, Canterbury, Notes and correspondence, 1982 February 18 (Folder 17)
    - Review of William E. Simon, Reforming the Income Tax System, The Banker, Typescript, 1981, 1982 February 24 (Folder 18)
    - "Let the Englishman Lay Down His Burden of the Welfare State," Daily Telegraph, printed copy, 1982 March 4 (Folder 19)
    - "Escape from British Health Service Is Accelerating," Miami Herald, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence. Includes an issue of the weekly Viewpoint (Miami Herald), 1982-1981 (Folder 20)
    - "The Biggest Con-Trick of Them All," Daily Mail, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1982 March 24 (Box 360, Folder 1)
    - Comment on G. Tullock's paper, European Public Choice Meeting, Faculté de Sciences Economiques et de Gestion, Université de Poitiers, Notes and correspondence. Includes participants' abstracts and conference papers, 1982 March 25 (Folder 2-3)
    - "The Inherent Contradiction Between Consumer Choice and Central Direction," lecture, Health Service Treasurers conference, University of Sussex, Brighton, Typescript and correspondence, 1982 April 3 (Folder 4)
    - "Tawney and the Social Democrats," Typescript, 1982 April 20 (Folder 5)
    - "Wither the Welfare State: The Undeveloped Scope for Permanent Insurance," Permanent Health Insurance Seminar, National Employers Life Group of Companies (NEL), Brighton (Great Britain), and York (Great Britain), Typescript, correspondence, NEL brochures, and paper by N. A. Hoffman, 1982 April 22, 1983 April 21 (Folder 6)
    - "Escaping the Socialist Illusion of Selflessness," Guardian, printed copy, 1982 May 31 (Folder 7)
    - "British Economic Policy under Margaret Thatcher," lecture, Centro de Estudios y Comunicación Económica, Madrid, Typescript, correspondence, clippings, and brochure, 1982 June 1 (Folder 8)
    - Participation in televised round-table debate on "This House Believes that the Public Sector Is not Organised in the Interests of the Public," Chartered Institute of Public Finance and Accountancy (CIPFA) Conference, Harrogate, Notes, typescript, correspondence, and conference program. Includes A. Seldon's article "Is the Public Sector Organised in the Interests of the Public?" Public Finance and Accountancy, Typescript and printed copy, 1982 (Box 361, Folder 1)
    - "Now the Whole Country Isn't Working - and Some People Like It that Way," Tribune, printed copy, 1982 August 13 (Folder 2)
    - "The Truth about Unemployment," Daily Telegraph, printed copy and correspondence, 1982 August 17 (Folder 3)
    - "Enhancement of Public Sector Efficiency by Micro-Economic Control of Public Supply," International Institute of Public Finance (IIPF) Congress, Copenhagen, Consecutively published in Economica delle scelte pubbliche, 1983, and in Public Finance and the Quest for Efficiency (Proceedings...), Typescript, galleys, correspondence, conference papers, and program, 1982-1984 (Folder 4-6)
    - "The Trend Towards Private Welfare," Free Nation, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1982 October (Folder 7)
    - "Will the Alliance Win the Race to Emancipate the Emerging Masses?" Alliance, Typescript and correspondence. See also Article on vouchers in education, 1983 July, 1982 October (Folder 8)
    - "Programme for the Second and Third Thatcherite Governments," talk, South Eastern Area Young Conservatives Meeting, Brighton, Typescript, correspondence, and flyer, 1982 October 5 (Folder 9)
    - "Is the Public Sector Organised in the Interests of the Public?" Public Finance and Accountancy, Typescript and printed copy. See Participation in televised round-table debate on "This House Believes that the Public Sector Is not Organised in the Interests of the Public," 1982 June 3, 1982 November
    - Round-table debate on "This House believes that Capitalism Has Failed," Durham Union Society Meeting, Durham, Notes, program, and correspondence. Includes typescript "Capitalism or Socialism: Which Has Failed?" Free Nation, 1982 November 12, undated (Folder 10)
    - "The Price of Health," lecture, Medical Society of London, Notes, transcript (published in Transactions of the Medical Society of London), and correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 362, Folder 1)
    - "Private Medicine Is Inevitable," Sunday Telegraph, Typescript and correspondence, 1982 December 13 (Folder 2)
    - "Accountability and Participation," Times Higher Education Supplement, Typescript and correspondence, 1982 December 17 (Folder 3)
    - "An Appreciation of W. H. Hutt," Manhatten Report, vol. III, No. 5. Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1983 (Folder 4)
    - "The British Welfare State: And the Lessons for Italy," La Crisi dello stato assistenziale, Typescript and correspondence, 1983 (Folder 5)
    - "Unemployment Is a Lingering Legacy of Inflation," Times, [?]. Typescript, correspondence, and background material, 1983 (Folder 6)
    - "The New Economics," Hacienda publica española, no. 20, and Journal of Social, Political and Economic Studies, vol. 8, no. 1, 1983
      - Typescript and printed copy of JSPES issue (Folder 7)
      - Correspondence
        - Castro, Jose V. (Folder 8)
        - Institut Economique de Paris (Henri Lepage/Guy Plunier) (Folder 9)
        - Lindsay, Greg (Centre for Independent Studies) (Folder 10)
        - Pearson, Roger (JSPES) (Folder 11)
        - Willgerodt, Hans (ORDO). Includes annotated typescript (Folder 12)
        - Miscellaneous. Various addressees (Folder 13)
    - "The Common Market as a 'Public Good,'" Wall Street Journal, Typescript, printed copy, correspondence and clippings, 1983 March 15 (Folder 14)
    - "All Mrs. Thatcher Has Done Is Voice the People's Views," Daily Telegraph, [?]. Galleys, typescript, and correspondence, 1983 April (Folder 15)
    - Comments on paper by K. S. Palda, European Public Choice Society meeting, Hanstholm (Denmark), Notes and correspondence. Includes paper by K. Hagedorn and brochure of the Federal Research Center of Agriculture in Braunschweig-Völkenrode (Germany), 1983 April 13 (Folder 16)
    - "The Disease of 'Free'-Dom and the Cure: Drug Costs in Britain and Europe," Colloquium, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence. Includes typescript by C. M. Lindsay and four other Colloquium issues, 1983 May (Box 363, Folder 1)
    - Transcript of debate with N. Bosanquet and M. Peston, World Medicine, Correspondence, 1983 May 14 (Folder 2)
    - "The Welfare State and Its Aftermath: New Economic and Social Trends," international conference in memory of Ehud Avriel, The Jerusalem Institute for Israel Studies, Jerusalem (Israel), Subsequently published in The Welfare State and Its Aftermath, Notes, typescript, correspondence, program, and conference papers, 1983-1984 (Folder 3-5)
    - Letter to the editor, Financial Times, Holograph and typescript, 1983 June 1 (Folder 6)
    - Two letters to the editor (referring to the letter to the editor by Ben Griffith, attached), Daily Telegraph, Typescripts, 1983 May 11 and June 3 (Folder 7)
    - "The Welfare State," lecture, Lehigh University Alumni meeting, London, Correspondence, 1983 June 21 (Folder 8)
    - "Pricing Policy for Public Services," lecture, European Institute of Public Administration (EIPA) colloquium, Maastricht (Netherlands), Subsequently published in Privatization and Deregulation: The European Debate, Notes, typescript, correspondence, and conference papers, 1983-1985 (Box 364, Folder 1-2)
    - Article on education vouchers, New Democrat, Correspondence and response by A. Sofer, 1983 July (Folder 3)
    - "The Disintegration of the N.H.S.," lecture, First European Libertarian Convention, Brussels, Typescript, correspondence, and program. Includes paper by F. Rutten, 1983 August 17 (Folder 4)
    - "The Pricing of Social Services," proposed paper, International Institute of Public Finance (IIPF) congress, Budapest, Synopsis, correspondence, and program, 1983 August 22-26 (Folder 5)
    - Comments on paper by C. Brunie, Mont Pèlerin Society regional meeting, Vancouver, Typescript, conference papers, program, and correspondence, 1983 September 1 (Folder 6-7)
    - Presentation of I.E.A. publications program, Atlas Economic Research Foundation seminar, Vancouver, Correspondence and conference program. Includes paper by J. Burton, 1983 September 2 (Box 365, Folder 1)
    - "More Hope for the Market in Britain's New Polity," Reason, Typescript and correspondence. Includes letter to the editor of Reason, 1983-1984 (Folder 2)
    - "Thatcher's Britain: Success or Failure?" lecture, Centro Ricerche Economiche Applicate (CREA), Rome, and Milano, Notes, typescript, summary in Italian and English, correspondence, and program, 1983 November 7-8 (Folder 3)
    - Foreword to Lewis Whyte, One Increasing Purpose: The Annals of an Investor, Typescript and correspondence. Includes L. Whyte's typescript, 1984 (Folder 4-5)
    - Socialism Explained (with Brian Crozier), (second edition entitled Socialism: The Grand Delusion, 1986), Correspondence with, 1984
      - Axel Springer Publishing Group (Folder 6)
      - Barron, Louis (Folder 7)
      - Crozier, Brian (Folder 8)
      - David Higham Associates (Folder 9)
      - Sherwood Press (Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 11)
    - "Freedom, Markets, and the Economic Role of Government," lecture, Civil Service College, London, Notes and correspondence, 1984 January 12 (Folder 12)
    - "The Moral Initiative in Medical Care," Typescript, 1984 March 7 (Folder 13)
    - Comment on paper by L. Sirc, conference on Yugoslavia, Institute for European Defense and Strategic Studies, London, Typescript and correspondence. Includes paper by L. Sirc and correspondence with L. Sirc and S. Stankovic, 1984 April 5 (Folder 14)
    - "The Burgeoning Market for Private Health Care," lecture, Mercantile and General Reinsurance symposium, London, Subsequently published in Proceedings of the Mercantile and General Reinsurance Company [?]. Typescript, brochures, and correspondence, 1984 May 23 (Box 366, Folder 1)
    - Contribution, "Current Economic Policy: A Two-Day Course for Economics Teachers," School of the Social Sciences and Business Studies, The Polytechnic of Central London, Handwritten outline, correspondence and program, 1984 June 6-7 (Folder 2)
    - Remarks, 2nd World Libertarian Convention, Royal Holloway College, Handwritten outline, notes, correspondence, and program, 1984 August 13-19 (Folder 3)
    - Participation, Atlas Economic Research Foundation autumn seminar, Cambridge, England, Correspondence. Includes correspondence from Antony Fisher to Martin Wessell, 1984 September 2 (Folder 4)
    - Remarks on the welfare state, Libertarian Alliance, London, (Seldon canceled his appearance). Correspondence and handwritten outline, 1984 September 30 (Folder 5)
    - "Private Welfare vs. Public Welfare," paper, 'State and Statism' Conference, Manchester Central Constituency Young Conservatives, Manchester University, Manchester, handwritten outline, correspondence and program, 1984 October 20 (Folder 6)
    - "Obstacles to De-Nationalizing the N.H.S.," paper The Selsdon Group Half-Day Conference, Institute of Directors, Handwritten outline, correspondence, and program, 1984 November 2 (Folder 7)
    - "The Next Ten Years: Can Government 'Hold' Its Expenditure?" Daily Telegraph, Typescript and correspondence, 1984 August 6 (Folder 8)
    - "New Right" Enlightenment: The Spectre that Haunts the Left, 1985
      - Lists of contributors, patrons, advisory board members, etc. (Folder 9)
      - Foreword (note) by F. A. von Hayek, "Socialism, Liberalism and the Young." Typescript and correspondence (Folder 10)
      - Introduction by A. Seldon. Typescript (Folder 11)
      - Reviews (Folder 12)
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - General. Letters (mainly master copies) re all stages of editing and distribution. Includes press release (Folder 13)
          - Contributors
            - Acceptances
              - Anderson, Martin J. (Folder 14)
              - Ashford, Nigel (Folder 15)
              - Burton, John (Folder 16)
              - Clarke, Peter (Folder 17)
              - Daljord, Marilyn (Folder 18)
              - Davies, Stephen (Box 367, Folder 1)
              - Dawson, Graham (Folder 2)
              - Glendenning, Marc H. (Folder 3)
              - Green, David (Folder 4)
              - Janman, Tim (Folder 5)
              - Knight, Christopher (Folder 6)
              - Kukathas, Chandran (Folder 7)
              - Lynn, Mathew (Folder 8)
              - Melnyk, Andrew (Folder 9)
              - Micklethwait, Brian (Folder 10)
              - Miller, Robert (Folder 11)
              - Parrett, Jenet (Folder 12)
              - Saunders, Peter (Folder 13)
              - Smith, Mark (Folder 14)
              - Tame, Chris (Folder 15)
            - Refusals (Folder 16)
          - Booksellers, individuals, newspapers, etc., re distribution
            - A-F (Folder 17)
            - G-L (Folder 18)
            - M-Z (Box 368, Folder 1)
          - Universities and colleges (Folder 2)
        - Unidentified (Folder 3)
        - Alternative Bookshop (Folder 4)
        - Ash, Michael (Folder 5)
        - Barron, Louis (Universe Books) (Folder 6)
        - Lucas, Terence (Folder 7)
        - Mockford, Gordon (Goron Pro-Print) (Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 9)
    - "Liberalism at/through the Mont Pèlerin Society: The British Experience," Liberty Fund conference, Freiburg i.Br. (Germany), 1985 March 24
      - Typescript (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence (Folder 11)
      - Conference papers by others (Folder 12)
    - "The Fate of the Education Voucher: The British Experience, 1981-1983," Liberty Fund conference, Baden-Baden (Germany), 1985 May 8
      - Typescript (Folder 13)
      - Correspondence (Folder 14)
      - Papers (Box 369)
        - Lee, Dwight R. (Folder 1)
        - Lith, Ulrich van (Folder 2)
    - Review of Edward Smithies, The Black Economy in England since 1914, and Phillip Mattera, Off the Books: The Rise of the Underground Economy, Times Literary Supplement, Typescript (entitled "White Markets and Over-Governments") and printed copy, 1984-1985 (Folder 3)
    - Review of T. R. Machan and M. B. Johnson (eds.), Rights and Regulations, Economic Journal, Typescript and correspondence, 1985 September (Folder 4)
    - Letter to the editor, Times, Typescript, and correspondence with Ian Bradley and Peter Curwen, 1985 September 11 (Folder 5)
    - Article, Times, Typescript and correspondence, 1985 September 28 (Folder 6)
    - "What's Wrong with the 'New Right'?" Listener, Typescript, 1985 September 30 (Folder 7)
    - "Demos or Demos," Spectator and Daily Telegraph, Typescript and correspondence, 1985 October 16 (Folder 8)